Today's דף daf, *daf* is ל"א *lamed-aleph*, 31, and we are continuing
on or at least start on ל' עמוד ב' *lamed-amud-bet* and we're
continuing on a fascinating discussion about if somebody is suspect for one
thing, do we suspect them for other things, where the דין din
*din* of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* is very much general
that חשוד לדבר אחד חשוד לכל התורה כולה *chashud l'davar echad chashud
l'chol hatorah kulah*, pretty hard to live your life that way, maybe
it's connected also to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* is חושש
לספק *choshesh l'safek*. Anyway, we say that people compartmentalize and even from
חמור *chamur* to a קל *kal*, you're not necessarily suspect if they
are some if it's a different type of a category. And part
of the and part of the challenge is determining what that category
is. And then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* also got into fascinating discussions
about גר ger *ger* and there it went beyond the question about
suspect and also questions about do you accept somebody if they're not
willing to fully accept the responsibilities, the obligations of the group. And
we talked about some major different interpretations about that in terms of
a גר *ger*. Anyway, now we pick up right after the parenthesis
in the middle of ל' עמוד ב' *lamed-amud-bet*, about 20 lines down
in the wide lines, and it says תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan, *Tanu
Rabbanan*: הבא לקבל דברי חברות chaverus. צריך לקבל בפני שלשה חברים chaverim?
*haba l'kabel divrei chaverus tzarich l'kabel bifnei shlosha chaveirim*. If somebody wants
to accept the sort of the these responsibilities, you know, of membership
essentially and become a member of this חבר chaver. *chaver* group, which
is about as I said primarily about טהרות taharos. *taharos* and particularly
around eating issues and so on and תרומות ומעשרות Umasros, *trumos u'maasros*,
then you have to do it in a formal process in front
of three other חברים chaverim *chaveirim*, so it's sort of like a
בית דין beis din. *beis din* but the representatives of three other
חברים chaverim *chaveirim*. ובניו ובני ביתו אין צריכים לקבל בפני שלשה חברים
chaverim *u'banav u'vnei beiso ein tzrichim l'kabel bifnei shlosha chaveirim*, but his
family, his children and the members of his house. Who are the
members of his house if not his children?
Slaves. Okay, who else? His wife. Okay, so that's maybe. Yeah,
I know, but it's clear that it includes his wife, we will
see. So anyway, they do not have to do a formal acceptance.
Presumably if the father has accepted or the husband has accepted the
what is it called pater familias then he will determine the behavior
of the household.
Which is often, you know, different than as we find highly nowadays
if in a couple if one is פרום *frum* and the other
one is
not is not observant, very often it's the woman who more determines
the basic standards in the house. Anyway, in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
it was it was it was not the wife but the husband
and the father. So he accepts it and his family is assumed
to follow along. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, בן גמליאל אומר אף בניו
ובני ביתו צריכים לקבל בפני שלשה חברים chaverim *Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel
omer af banav u'vnei beiso tzrichim l'kabel bifnei shlosha chaveirim*, even his
children and the members of his household have to do a formal
acceptance. Why? לפי שאינו דומה חבר chaver, שקיבל לבן חבר chaver, שקיבל
*lefi she'eino domeh chaver shekibel l'ven chaver shekibel*. It's not similar if
you accepted yourself or if you're the son of somebody who accepted.
So if you're just a child then it's not as much of
an acceptance of personal responsibility, I mean there's actually ambiguous what this
last line means but let's say that, and therefore it does you
will not necessarily keep to the same standard just because your father
has accepted. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says that that this line could also
be read according to according to the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* why
the child doesn't have to accept. Because when you are doing it
yourself then you need the you know and you don't have a
father who's doing it then you need to accept it personally but
if your father is doing it that already will naturally drag you
along and therefore you don't need to do it personally. So the
question is how do you read this last line? But more simply
it reads according to רבי שמעון בן גמליאל *Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel*.
תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*: הבא לקבל דברי חברות chaverus צריך
לקבל בפני ג' חברים chaverim ואפילו תלמיד חכם talmid chacham צריך לקבל
בפני שלשה חברים chaverim, *haba l'kabel divrei chaverus tzarich l'kabel bifnei gimmel
chaveirim v'afillu talmid chacham tzarich l'kabel bifnei shlosha chaveirim*. Even a תורה
Torah *Torah* sage has to accept before three חברים Chaveirim *chaveirim*, and
this really points to the fact that as I was telling you
yesterday that the institution of חברות *chaverus* is different than the institution
than the and
the חברים chaveirim *chaveirim* were different than the תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim.
*talmidei chachamim*. Right, the תלמיד חכם talmid chacham *talmid chacham* are the
sages and the people that spend all their time learning גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara*, the חברים chaverim? *chaveirim* are the people that spend all their
time being careful about טומאה וטהרה Tumah Vetaharah. *tumah v'taharah* and תרומות
ומעשרות *trumos u'maasros*. So obviously since that means of halachic scrupulousness although
some of it is being more careful than necessary, חולין בטהרה chullin
be-tahara. *chullin b'taharah* that a lot of it, so there's un- it's
not so surprising that there's an overlap but they're fundamentally two different
groups. Okay, so it if even if you're a תלמיד חכם talmid
chacham, *talmid chacham* you have to go through this formal process. זקן
ויושב בישיבה zaken ve-yoshev bi-yeshiva *zaken v'yoshev b'yeshiva*, however if you are
an elder and sitting in a ישיבה *yeshiva*. Now exactly what that
phrase means is not fully clear. Does it mean like you're sitting
on a בית דין beis din *beis din*? Does it mean that
you have a particular type of a post in the community or
do you mean literally you're in a ישיבה *yeshiva*, you're like you
give a שיעור *shiur* in a ישיבה *yeshiva*? Anyway, אינו צריך לקבל
בפני שלשה שכבר קיבל עליו משעה שישב *eino tzarich l'kabel bifnei shlosha
shekvar kibel alav misha'ah sheyashav*, you do not need to accept because
you already accepted at implicitly, explicitly, maybe implicitly but explicitly you don't
need to tell me this when you were appointed. So somehow there
was a certain role, the רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* in in his משנה
תורה Mishneh Torah *Mishneh Torah* does not explicate this, but there was
a certain role of זקן ויושב בישיבה *zaken v'yoshev b'yeshiva* which was
assumed to implicitly you know be an acceptance of being a חבר
chaver *chaver*. All right, but what is important is is that these
are different groups and different identities although they overlap. But somehow there
was this certain role, the רמב"ם Rambam in משנה mishna תורה does
not explicate this, but there was a certain role of זקן ויושב
בישיבה which was assumed to implicitly be an acceptance of being a
חבר. chaver. Alright, but what is important is that these are different
groups and different identities, although there is often a lot of overlap.
But yes, what if you say it's implicit, then what about the
requirement to do it בפני שלושה?
bifnei sheloshah? But בפני שלושה bifnei sheloshah is not like גירות. geirus.
It's not like there's a formal halakhic change of status. It's more
like, you know, that these are the almost the rules of the
community. Yeah, I mean, the way in which the community has to
acknowledge that it's accepting its members,
right, to such a position.
Exactly. Exactly. Because if it were explicit, you could read it as
explicit, but then what's the point of saying this? So then there's
only one thing: somebody already did it, doesn't have to do it
again. Right? So I think you can only reasonably read it as
implicit. But right, it's not like somebody could say a גר in
certain circumstances doesn't need a בית דין. Beis Din. There's not a
halakhic formal בית דין Beis Din that affects the change of status,
right? This is... I mean, it is a type of maybe modeled
after that. Your status is now that of חבר, chaver. but it's
all, you know, basically the rules of the club. So... and that's...
and that's sort of the way, you know, what's going on here.
The גמרא Gemara frequently refers to the idea of a חבר, chaver
but I was unaware that there was a formal kind of procedure
in the only place that comes out.
Yeah, I mean, this comes up in דמאי. Demai. A lot of
this is taken from the תוספתא דמאי Tosefta Demai because דמאי Demai
talks a lot about what it means to be, whether you're חשודין
chashudin as being a חבר chaver and to be accepted as a
חבר. chaver But yes, this is like the primary material. It gets
repeated in one or two places, but this is the primary material.
And is this the kind of model for the German, the Ashkenazi
practice of calling leaders of the community חברים?
Yeah, that very well could be. Yeah, I assume so, right? Exactly.
Well, well, that's exactly what I was going to say. You know,
here you see what's very important about this גמרא Gemara is you
see that just because you're a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham doesn't mean
you're a חבר. chaver. You need to accept. We're actually going to
read a story in a minute that's actually going to even highlight
the different nature of the membership of the group. But, yes, when
you read... when... if you're not... if you're just reading the גמרא,
Gemara you assume, you know, who's a חבר chaver contrasted to עם
הארץ? am ha-aretz? Who else is contrasted to עם הארץ? am ha-aretz?
תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim And there's basically an assumption that חבר chaver
is תלמיד חכם talmid chacham to the point that the רמב"ם in
פירוש המשניות Perush Ha-Mishnayos basically says, 'Oh, חברים really means תלמידי חכמים
talmidei chachamim. because they're the only ones who have a true sense
of friendship because it's a friendship based on, you know, לשם שמים
leshem shamayim and based on sort of shared religious and intellectual pursuits.'
So he basically reinterprets the phrase חבר chaver, to essentially mean תלמיד
חכם, talmid chacham but it is clear that right, that yes, that
that already evolution began in the גמרא Gemara... and yeah, I had
forgotten about that nice point about that Ashkenazi practice and continued afterwards.
Even if you're not a תלמיד חכם talmid chacham nor somebody who's
particularly careful about any area of הלכה. halakhah.
Right, just somebody who's like has a leadership role.
Traditional kind of...
right, exactly. That's a good point.
It's more of a model for behavior. Aha.
But somebody who is not only a leader but you mean but
also someone that is like a role model in terms of their
character and personal... ah, I see. Okay, so that's nice. So then
that way maybe... right, but there's a certain type of like scrupulousness
of behavior which... oh that's a nice point. That's nice. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara. goes on. אבא שאול אומר אף תלמיד חכם
אינו צריך לקבל בפני שלושה חברים. Abba Shaul omer af talmid chacham
eino tzarich lekabel bifnei sheloshah chaverim. A תלמיד חכם talmid chacham does
not need to, and here I think we are actually seeing the
insistence that to not... to... to sort of, you know, to merge
the two identities. That a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham, doesn't need to
be מקבל, mekabel, that a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham? by definition is
a חבר. chaver, And here I think what we're getting and you'll
see as the גמרא Gemara, continues actually the historical point about how
the two identities
merged. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, said רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
בימי בנו של רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס נישנית משנה זו. bimei beno
shel Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos nishnes mishna zu.
This משנה Mishnah. where first they were recognized... they were... they were
seen as separate and a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham, had to formally
become a חבר chaver was taught in the time of the son
of רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס. Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos. What does that
mean? So the גמרא... Gemara so we'll see in the גמרא. Gemara
Let's take a look. רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי איסתפק להו מילתא בטהרות.
Rabbi Yehuda ve-Rabbi Yosi istapak lehu milta be-taharos. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and רבי יוסי... Rabbi Yosi... תנאים, Tannaim,
students of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
had a doubt in a matter relating to טהרות. taharos שדרו רבנן
לגבי בנו של רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס. Shadro rabanan legabi b'no shel
Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonus.
They sent to the son of רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס, Rabbi Chanina
ben Antigonus, who we are going to see was a כהן, Kohen,
and that's interesting. So they might have been sending to him because
he's just a תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham, but they might have been
sending to him because of course who knows טהרות taharos, better than
a כהן Kohen who is a תלמיד חכם? Talmid Chacham And again
talking about different sort of roles and statuses, you know, post בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, the significance of כהן, Kohen, who used to be
the religious leaders, fell totally by the wayside. But maybe, you know,
still in the area of טהרות, taharos. you know, maybe there was
still a particular sort of acknowledgment that they were the more expert.
So anyway, they sent to רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס. Rabbi Chanina ben
Antigonus. אזילו אמרו ליה לעיין בה. Azilu amru lei l'ayin bah.
So they sent, so maybe they sent people to go in their
stead to go as their emissaries and they said and they said
to the, אמרו ליה לעיין בה, amru lei l'ayin bah, and
to look into it. אשכחוה דקא טעין טהרות. Ashkuchuah de'ka tain taharos.
So, or אמרו ליה, amru lei,
I'm just trying to get here the... maybe they sent, they went
and they said to a person, maybe it's אמרו להו? amru lehu?
Does the י״א Yud Aleph change it? No. אנטיגנוס אזילו אמרו ליה,
Antigonus, azilu amru lei, אמרו ליה לעיין בה. amru lei l'ayin bah.
Okay, anyway, go and say to him to look into it for
us and to give us an answer about what is this story
with טהרות. taharos, So אשכחוה דקא טעין טהרות, ashkuchuah de'ka tain taharos,
they saw that he was carrying or watching, the cite says נטר,
natar, he was watching טהרות, taharos. watching certain food preventing it from
becoming טמא. tamei. So אוזי רבנן מדידיה לגביהו. osi rabanan mididei legabeihu.
He said, I'm sorry, I can't help you, I'm too busy watching
these טהרות. taharos. He sent one of his students, a rabbi from
his group, you know, to go, go help these guys. I'm too
busy watching
טהרות. taharos. Go help them answer their question. וקאי הו ליוני בה.
Veka'ihu leyunei bah.
And he went to look into it for the rabbis that had
this question, but רבי... בנו של רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rabbi... b'no
shel Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonus was too busy watching his טהרות. taharos
אתו אמרו ליה לרבי יוסי ורבי יהודה. Asu amru lei l'Rabbi Yosi
v'Rabbi Yehuda. So the people that רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda sent to, of course you notice a little bit
of an irony here, they're going to be offended but they themselves
didn't go personally, right? They sent people for them to ask the
question. But then the person that they were asking, the son of
רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonus himself, was too busy
and he sent somebody to take care of it. So anyway, the
people that were sent by רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda went back and said to them. So אמר להו רבי
יהודה, amar lehu Rabbi Yehuda, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said to
these messengers, אביו של זה ביזה תלמידי חכמים. aviv shel zeh bizeh
talmidei chachamim. This person's father denigrated תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim. אף הוא
מבזה תלמידי חכמים. Af hu mevazeh talmidei chachamim. Look, it runs in
the family, he also was מבזה, mevazeh, denigrated תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim,
Now רש״י Rashi says it never really happened that his father did.
He was just angry, so he said, I bet his father did
it too. So תוספות Tosfos says, look at תוספות, Tosfos, על טהרות
כמו שעשה בנו. al taharos k'mo she'asa b'no. That we never heard
that רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rabbi Chanina ben Antigonus was מבזה, mevazeh,
but תוספות Tosfos makes it sound like it wasn't just in a
state of anger. Maybe there really was some case that there was
an issue of טהרות taharos. and he wasn't giving us respect, he
was too busy with his טהרות. taharos. He didn't want, you know,
and this person, so they were very angry that he was sort
of holding his position over them and not giving them respect.
Now, by the way, again the תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, they might
not be referring to themselves, right? The תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, תלמידי
חכמים, talmidei chachamim often we think it means, oh, the biggest sage
is a תלמיד חכם, Talmid Chacham but תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim. more
technically is the student of sages. And that they mean is the
students, their students that they sent to ask a question, those were
the תלמידי חכמים. talmidei chachamim, Okay? But again, notice the irony. They're
so offended, but they sent their student, he sent his student. Okay?
But no, he should have responded, which basically in my mind means
that it was clear who was the bigger acknowledged sage. רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, of course, are the, you
know, they are the major תנאים. Tannaim. רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס, Rabbi
Chanina ben Antigonus, whoever he is, and him, he was somebody who,
okay, he had scholarship and whatever, he was תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham.
but his field was טהרות. taharos He wasn't like the same acknowledged
sage. So they were very offended. Clearly, in their mind, the hierarchy
is that the bigger Torah sages win. Okay? But he was holding
himself apart, not as a bigger Torah sage, but because as somebody
who was particularly scrupulous about טהרות taharos and can't take himself away
from that role to help the Torah sages. And this is really
then what you get is the competition of these two groupings and
identity, right? The grouping of תלמידי חכמים, Talmidei Chachamim. of sages, of
חכמים chachamim as one type of identity which, you know, clearly is
being held supreme. But then there's the identity of חבר chaver. and
טהרות taharos and maybe ex... not ex-כהנים, Kohanim, but people who had
been, you know, כהנים Kohanim who no longer were working in the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And that's a very different type of an
identity. And here there was a little sense of being offended and
competition and acknowledging who's greater. So let's take a look. So it
says אמר לו רבי יוסי, amar lo Rabbi Yosi, so רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yosi said to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who was getting so
upset, כבוד זקן הם מונחים במקומן. kvod zakein hein munachim bimkomon.
The respect of the elders should be left in its place, meaning
could mean just his father, but רש״י Rashi says him as well.
Let's, let's not go ahead and say he's such a bad guy.
He's a good guy.
אלא מי. Ela mi. From the day the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash has
been destroyed, נהגו כהנים סלסול בעצמן, nagu kohanim silsul be-atzman,
interesting phrase, the כהנים kohanim have given like themselves a sort of,
you know, a special status, have given themselves this sort of high
status בעצמן, be-atzman, שאין מוסרין את הטהרה לכל אדם, she-ein mosrin es
ha-tahara le-chol adam,
they do not allow other people to watch their טהרה, tahara, so
you know you said, why didn't he, why didn't he come and
answer our question, he could have had somebody else watch it for
him. No no no no no, חכמים Chachamim are very focused on,
you know, on this special role of theirs and they will not
give anybody else, even somebody like חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Chanina ben Antigonos
can't leave that to answer your question, they will not give it
to anybody else. Now again, the implication of this, first of all
by the way anybody who knows, you know, we're reading right now
this week's פרשה parsha about יוסף, Yosef, right? And הוא נער את
בני בלהה ואת בני זלפה, hu na'ar es bnei Bilhah ve-es bnei
Zilpah,
so he was a child with the sons of Bilhah and Zilpah.
So the famous מדרש Midrash is that he was too busy being
מסלסל בשערו, misalsel bis’aro, he was too busy like you know, like
sort of playing with the locks of his hair and looking about
how beautiful he was, he was doing you know very childish types
of things. סלסול silsul is not necessarily a compliment, okay? It means
somebody that's like you know always sort of taking you know looking
at themselves in the mirror and attending to how beautiful they are
and their looks and so on, which also like so it's funny
in the same way he said כבוד, kavod, you know let his
כבוד kavod remain, there's a sense like the כהנים, kohanim, although the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is destroyed, what are they doing? They're holding
on to an aspect of their special status by being very scrupulous
about טהרה tahara and not letting anybody else take it, which is
basically saying they're holding on to this element of their status and
it's סלסול בעצמן, silsul be-atzman, it's a way of holding themselves a
little bit higher and a little bit separate, okay? But I think
that there's a subtext, while it's saying let's not denigrate him, the
subtext is, you know, let's respect that that approach, that behavior, although
we really know that the real כבוד kavod goes to the תלמידי
חכמים. Talmidei Chachamim. Okay, so what you actually see here is these
two different groups, and in fact it's כהנים וחברים kohanim ve-chaverim and
so on and תלמידי חכמים. Talmidei Chachamim So when the גמרא, Gemara
so now how does this fit into what we said before? Because
we were saying when did we say that a תלמיד חכם Talmid
Chacham. has to formally accept and become a חבר, chaver. that was
in this period when they were still basically separate groups and somebody
like חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Chanina ben Antigonos son of חנינא בן אנטיגנוס
Chanina ben Antigonos would not allow you know somebody else to watch
his טהרה tahara even תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim and so on, it
was very very much about being a special separate group and being
a תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham. did not mean you were member of
the other group. Okay, but obviously the emphasis is we all know
who
really is the more important group and ultimately then after this period
תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim became identified as חברים as well and therefore
no longer needed a formal acceptance. Yes?
What is he actually exactly watching
someone's טהרה? tahara?
What? I don't know, like why do you have to watch it?
You know, maybe you're transporting it and you have to make sure
that on the road things don't fly in the way and you
don't you know you don't touch a נבילה neveila or something. תרומה?
Trumah? No, it could even
be תרומה trumah but it could even be חולין chullin because part
of the חברים were they ate their חולין בטהרה. chullin betaharah, Okay,
so what I think is fascinating about this גמרא Gemara is that
you really get an acknowledgment of the historical change and how two
groups essentially became their you know their identity became conflated and one
of them morphed into into the other.
Okay, so now we continue and again like I said you know
the רמב"ם says חברים means תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim because that's what
true fellowship is about. Okay, anyway so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan:
חבר שמת, chaver she-meis, now we're going back to the question about
if a person became this חבר, chaver. would the assumptions that that
maintains in terms of the rest of his family, that then the
rest of his family follows follows along? So if a חבר chaver,
died, so now the family does not have the father figure and
the husband to determine the behavior. What are the status of the
kids and the and the and the wife who never formally accepted
the status of חברים themselves? אשתו ובניו ובני ביתו הרי הן בחזקתן
עד שיחשדו. ishto uvanav uvnei beiso harei hein be-chezkasan ad she-yeichasheidu. We
assume that they retain their role as חברים, first of all their
status, they have they do have that status once the father husband
got it, it applies to them directly, they own that status, they
don't lose it on his death and they're assumed to that their
behavior will live up to it even without the father along, once
they have been raised that way or once the wife has been
married to the husband. Okay, וכן חצר שמוכרין בה תכלת, ve-chein chatzer
she-mochrin bah techeiles, similarly let's say there was a courtyard like a
you know where a square where they used to sell תכלת techeiles
and there was always the question about whether they were going to
have false תכלת techeiles indigo as a fake תכלת techeiles and you
know you make a much bigger profit if you don't have need
the real תכלת. techeiles. הרי היא בחזקתה עד שתפסל, harei hi be-chezkasah
ad she-tipaseil, once it was known that they were selling the real
תכלת, techeiles, you assume that people will continue to be careful about
that unless you have particular evidence otherwise, you don't need to do
regular testing. Of course, that seems to be given to a lot
of abuse. Once you get the reputation for selling תכלת, techeiles, if
nobody's doing regular checkups, so that's an interesting analogy as opposed to
the other one, which is a question about just people that have
been raised with a certain type of behavior in terms of what
their sort of religious norms are. Now this is a question about
honesty of merchants, which is, you could imagine, very different.
Is it since the father is doing the business?
No, no, no, it's a totally different סוגיא. sugya. Just as by
analogy, just as the family retains its behavior, we assume that the
people who sell the תכלת techeiles will keep on doing the same
thing. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan, We're at the top. תנו
רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan, אשת עם הארץ שנשאת לחבר. eshes am ha'aretz shenisais
l'chaver. Now, let's say the wife of an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz,
and the עם הארץ am ha'aretz died or divorced her, and then
she got married to a חבר. chaver, Okay, so we already pretty
much know that the גמרא Gemara is assuming that the behavior of
the wife and the children follow the husband, but let's—or husband-father—but let's
take a look. וכן בתו של עם הארץ שנשאת לחבר, v'chein bito
shel am ha'aretz shenisais l'chaver, or the daughter of an עם הארץ
am ha'aretz whose practice was following that of an עם הארץ am
ha'aretz and now she married a חבר. chaver, וכן עבדו של עם
הארץ שנמכר לחבר, v'chein avdo shel am ha'aretz shenimkar l'chaver, and that
might be what you people suggested was בני ביתו, bnei beiso, the
slave of an עם הארץ am ha'aretz is now sold to a
חבר. chaver כולם צריכין לקבל דברי חבירות בתחילה. kulam tzrichin l'kabel divrei
chaveirus bat'chila. Here, when did we say that the family members do
not need? That's when that was sort of their original, you know,
relationship. So somebody was, you know, so you buy a slave maybe
from a non-Jew, but he never sort of learned a different Jewish
practice.
You
know, so you're not marrying a divorced woman, it's her first marriage,
and the kids of course are born into that. So those types
of things we say will follow what the husband does. But if
it's—but if they were started with a different practice because they were
married, children, owned by an—by an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, then we
do not assume that they transform their practice immediately. They need to
go through a formal process of accepting it.
Okay. Except for—yes. I think that the חזקה שמכרן בתכלת, chazaka shemachran
b'techeiles, I think it's not referring to the person, but referring to
the
people in the court, but the market. Right.
But—and that's the analogy to חבר שמת. chaver shemeis. So even though
the person who originally accepted on himself חבירות chaveirus is no longer
there, it's like in the farmers' market, you're only going to get
fresh produce. Right. And they wouldn't—if somebody brought
California strawberries to the farmers' market, they wouldn't let them in anymore.
I see. That's an interesting point. Meaning, so—I—yes, I—I did—I did get
the point that it was—that it wasn't about the same person, it
was about the—the sort of—but what I didn't—what I didn't get, which
I appreciate your point, was what's keeping them honest? Meaning, in one
case, you're raised with certain religious standards, you naturally keep them up.
But in the another case, it's all about business. Who—what's keeping me
honest? So you want to say is, no, maybe it's the everybody
else in the market is keeping the people honest. That could very
well be. I appreciate that. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
Where are we?
Okay.
One minute. Okay, right. So now, by the way, the only problem
with the contrast about whether they were already habituated in a different
way is the case about בתו של עם הארץ. bito shel am
ha'aretz. Because if we said that when a—somebody becomes a חבר, Chaver,
the wife's status immediately changes as well, well, who did he marry?
Who was his wife? If his wife was a בת חבר, bas
chaver, so then she wouldn't need the husband's acceptance. And if the
wife was a בת עם הארץ, bas am ha'aretz, here we see
the husband's acceptance doesn't work for her. Right? You get the point?
So here's a בת עם הארץ bas am ha'aretz who marries a
חבר, Chaver the husband's acceptance doesn't work. So when is it that
the husband's acceptance does work for the wife? So רש״י Rashi says,
ah, it matters whether she was around when the person—when the husband
did the acceptance. Okay. That part of what makes this case even
more challenging is not just they were habituated differently, but when the
husband-father did his induction into the חבר, Chaver, these were not even
part of his family. And therefore, there was not sort of—it didn't
have the same impact on the family and their acknowledgment of their
responsibilities. So in this case where they were habituated differently and/or they
weren't there when the husband-father accepted his חבירות, chaveirus, they need to
accept it for themselves. And now it goes on and says, וכן,
v'chein, and the same is true in the
reverse. וכן בתו של חבר שנשאת לעם הארץ, v'chein bito shel chaver
shenisais l'am ha'aretz, וכן עבדו של חבר שנמכר לעם הארץ, v'chein avdo
shel chaver shenimkar l'am ha'aretz, אין צריכין לקבל—oh, ein tzrichin l'kabel wait,
I'm—אבל אשת חבר שנשאת לעם הארץ. aval eshes chaver shenisais l'am ha'aretz.
If it was the reverse, the חבר Chaver, died and his wife
married an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, וכן בתו של חבר שנשאת לעם
הארץ, v'chein bito shel chaver shenisais l'am ha'aretz, his daughter married, וכן
עבדו של חבר שנמכר לעם הארץ, v'chein avdo shel chaver shenimkar l'am
ha'aretz, his slave was sold to an
עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, אין צריכין לקבל דברי חבירות בתחילה. ein tzrichin
l'kabel divrei chaveirus bat'chila. Now that's a little bit surprising. Why? Once
they—this is much bigger than if the guy dies. Not only did—not
only is he no longer the sort of their father, husband, etc.,
but they are now married to or, you know, to an עם
הארץ, am ha'aretz, where you would think their behavior would naturally follow
their current family structure. No, they are still considered to be חבירים,
chaverim, which seems to be a very big
surprise.
רש״י—somewhere Rashi is רש״י...
Rashi... Yeah, I mean, that is what is really right, right, that
is is what is really shocking about this. רש"י Rashi, also says
that there's a whole question here anyway about the גירסא. Girsa. So
anyway, but yeah, that second line is certainly shocking. So now, רבי
מאיר אומר אף הן צריכין לקבל עליהם דברי חברות
לכתחילה. Rabbi Meir Omer Af Hein Tzerichin Lekabel Aleihem Divrei Chaveirus Lechatchila.
No, once they're in this new environment, if they want to retain
the status of חבר, Chaver. they need to accept it upon themselves
as they, you know, from the outset, which is makes a tremendous
amount of sense, especially as Dov says, right, the children and and
the slaves and, you know, even the wife in the time of
the גמרא Gemara did not really, even if they wanted to and
weren't just naturally influenced, really could not control their environment so well,
so much. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
yeah, if you look at רש"י, Rashi. right, it was רש"י. Rashi
אין צריכין לקבל, Ein Tzerichin Lekabel, רש"י Rashi says אם חזרו תחת
יד חבר. Im Chazru Tachas Yad Chaver. So רש"י Rashi basically says,
no, no, no, no, when they are married or owned by this
עם הארץ, Am Ha'aretz, of course we can't assume that they're keeping
up their standard. The question is, now this guy dies or divorces
and so on, and now they want to say, oh, we want
to go back to our original חבר Chaver status. Okay, so that's
how רש"י Rashi. understood it, right, exactly for this problem. How can
we assume these people, what's the, you know, are retaining their previous
behavior? They're not controlling their environment, they're influenced by their, by the
father, husband, and so on. So the answer is, no, no, no,
after they now, the guy died or divorced and so on, now
they want to reassert their past status. Okay, so the חכמים Chachamim
say that's okay, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no, they have
to re-accept. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר משום רבי מאיר מעשה באשה
אחת שנישאת לחבר והיתה קומטת תפילין על
ידו. Rabbi Shimon Ben Elazar Omer Mishum Rabbi Meir Maaseh Be'isha Achas
Shenises Lechaver Vehaysa Kometes Tefillin Al Yado. There's a story about the
wife, about a certain woman that was married to a חבר, Chaver,
so she took, she followed his religious standards and she helped him
wrap his תפילין. Tefillin. ונישאת, Venises, I don't know why he needed
that help. ונישאת לעם הארץ והיתה קושרת לו קשרי מוכס על ידו.
Venises Le'am Ha'aretz Vehaysa Kosheres Lo Kishrei Mochas Al Yado. She got
then then got married to an עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz and she
helped him tie up his little bundles of tax receipts. He was
a tax collector, which, by the way, tax collectors and חברים and
the people with this certain fellowship are often seen are often in
contrast throughout the gospels. Okay, anyway, so that's the point. Jesus would
eat with the tax collectors. They were like the people that were
seen as really oppositional somehow because whatever, not, you know, A, they
were connected to the government and B, they were whatever, you know,
there was a sense that they were stealing and, you know, the
tax burden, they were imposing too high a tax burden. So why
exactly that was like a contrast to חבר, chaver, you know, even
though they have all those bad qualities, is not so clear, but
that is actually the case. Anyway, the very fact that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir, gives this example seems to be not like רש"י. Rashi
It seems to be saying that it's not the question they got
divorced and now the question is do they go back to the
status. It seems like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. is emphasizing, right, this
is רבי שמעון, this is in the name of רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir he's emphasizing people's behavior will naturally follow their surroundings. And even
this פרומע Frum woman, once she married an עם הארץ, Am Ha'aretz,
is going to go by his lower standards. So therefore we have
to assume that their standards immediately adapt to their current marital, you
know, family situation. Okay, but again, that makes the חכמים's Chachamim position
harder, so רש"י Rashi assumes that we're talking after they get divorced,
after that. Okay. What?
Is there evidence for the husband's?
Well, yeah, but this was talking about more like I said, the
natural things that would happen, not הלכתית. Halachically. And the irony is
that
nowadays, you know, you'd get some exact statistics about it, but I
think it's very evident that that if there's different religious practices, the
the wife-mother's practice has usually a much stronger influence on the practices
of the household than the father's. That's at least my
sense. Might not be the same if it's an intermarried couple, but
if it's different degrees of
religiosity within, let's say, Judaism, then I think at least my impression
is that it's much more determined by the mother. Anyway, let's take
a look. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan. now we go on, we taught
another ברייתא, Braisa, this is a תוספתא Tosefta in דמאי. Demai. וכולן
שחזרו בהן אין מקבלין אותן לעולם דברי רבי מאיר. Vechulan Shechazru Bahen
Ein Mekablin Osan Le'olam Divrei Rabbi Meir. If any of now when
they if they went back, you do not accept them forever. These
are the words of רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir, What does it mean
went back? So רש"י Rashi has a complicated
read. תוספות's Tosafos read is the best. Basically what it means is
like this: somebody went ahead and they were חבר. chaver, Then they
backslided. Okay, and that and they, you know, whatever, they went so
so and now they want to become a so and now they
want to become a חבר chaver. again. Do we say that the
very fact that you had backsliding, you started off your life now
as a חבר, chaver you accepted, you accepted, and now you've reverted
to your old behavior? Okay, does the fact that you've reverted to
your old behavior mean we'll never be able to trust you again
because basically we see that you naturally revert back to to that
original behavior or not? And so here רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says...
Yeah, once you've done that, אין מקבלים אותו לעולם. ein mekabelim oso
le'olam. We don't accept you at all, which by the way fits
in with the way רש״י Rashi read the other רבי מאיר, Rebbi
Meir which is she was married to a חבר, chaver she got
married to an עם הארץ, am ha'aretz, we don't, although there it
was less drastic, there wasn't backsliding, but there רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir
was saying we don't assume that she naturally goes back to her
original state, she needs a formal acceptance. Anyway, so רבי מאיר Rebbi
Meir is concerned when people move around, how stable their position is.
So here, if there's been some backsliding, רבי מאיר says I don't
want to accept them ever again, you can't trust them into this
חברות. רבי יהודה אומר חזו במטמוניס אין מקבלין אותן בפרהסיא מקבלין אותן.
Rabbi Yehuda omer chazu b'matmonis ein mekabelin osan b'farhesya mekabelin osan. If
their backsliding happened in private and in public they went around acting
like they were חבר, chaver then you can't accept them again. Why?
Because then they've really demonstrated a lack of sincerity. Okay, meaning then
it's like it's very clear they want people to believe they're חברים
even though that's not their practice in private. So now they're saying
oh now I'm going to really be a חבר. chaver, Not only
have you demonstrated backsliding, you've actually demonstrated you know duplicity and the
fact that this is much more about appearances so we really cannot
trust you. However, בפרהסיא, b'farhesya, if the backsliding was public, look I
might not be the frummest person but I don't lie about it.
Okay? So if I've backslided then everybody knows. So now when I'm
saying that I want to do תשובה teshuva and I want to
work again at that higher standard, you can believe that I'm sincere.
You believe my sincerity, you believe my effort. The only question might
be whether actually you believe my ability to actually sustain that. But
they're willing
to be more generous and saying that in that case מקבלין אותן,
mekabelin osan, we would accept it. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, others say,
אם עשו דבריהם במטמוניס מקבלין אותן, im asu divreihem b'matmonis mekabelin osan,
that the if they did their thing, what thing? So it can't
mean they're sinning because that was exactly the point before. So תוספות
Tosfos says it means if even after the backsliding we see that
עשו דבריהם במטמוניס, asu divreihem b'matmonis, that they are privately still working
at keeping up their higher behavior then we see that they're really
still struggling with it and they're trying and so on then מקבלין
אותן, mekabelin osan, then you can accept them. Or maybe now that
they've said hey I want you to accept me again and you
see that even in private somehow you've got a peek into their
private lives that they're readopting their old standard, a higher standard, even
in private. Then you can believe the sincerity and therefore you can
accept them. However, if all we've seen is their public behavior that
it's the higher standard, the older higher standard and they're saying please
accept me again look I'm better than I was before look at
my public behavior, then we don't trust you. Maybe you're just doing
it for show and maybe in private you haven't. Okay? So אין
מקבלין אותן. ein mekabelin osan. How do you find out about their
private behavior?
Right, so exactly, so we can do a little peeping into their
private lives. Anyway I think that this is really fascinating because this
is so easily translatable into you know questions about, we don't have
that same sense of tight community but there are definitely people that
you know do certain things that you know sort of public things
which are not just sins but they're also actually you know unethical
behavior and so on and then they come and they say you
know certainly in cases like of sexual abuse and then they come
and they say they've done תשובה teshuva and they should be reaccepted
into the community and let bygones be bygones and so on. So
the question is you know the community also has to protect itself
and how much do you trust a person and so on and
everybody can do תשובה teshuva but also there's other considerations as well
you know and this גמרא Gemara is I think really important and
fascinating in terms of that question about the psychology and the sense
also that we don't necessarily just say oh everybody does תשובה teshuva
so of course we believe you. You know and the community has
to again protect its own integrity and so on. So the differences
here about number one the very things that are by naturally backsliding
you know and things that are pathologies also of things that are
really very natural backsliding so that's one area of questioning which is
the רבי מאיר and the other is right how sincere you are,
is there a duplicity, do we think that when you were you
know in the past when you sinned you know that you tried
to maintain a public face and so on so was there duplicity
in the sinning and is there possibly a duplicity in the תשובה.
teshuva. Maybe you're only saying it outwardly and not actually changing inwardly
and all those are questions here that are being asked. So I
think that this is a very important from that perspective. Let's take
a look. רבי שמעון ורבי יהושע בן קרחה אומרים בין כך ובין
כך מקבלין אותן, Rebbi Shimon v'Rebbi Yehoshua ben Korcha omrim beinkach u'beinkach
mekabelin osan, but here is the more inclusive approach. Regardless of any
of those things, public, private or whatever, and even whether past behavior
that they slid back to, you receive them שנאמר, shene'emar, the verse
says שובו בנים שובבים, shuvu banim shovavim, return, o
returning sons, and the שובבים, shovavim, the double שובב shovav suggests the
idea that you've returned many times.
So you kept on backsliding and returning and backsliding and returning and
we still say come back and do תשובה. teshuva. The doors of
תשובה teshuva are always open even even if you've had a lot
of problems with it and a lot of backsliding. So רב יצחק
איש כפר עכו אמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כוותייהו Rav Yitzchak Ish Kfar
Akko amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha kevoseihu and we rule like them. So
yeah, so the question I would say given my little sort of
analogy before is do we do we rule like them meaning that
those other concerns were irrelevant? It's one thing to accept them back
into חברות which is what's the degree of risk if you accept
them back as חברים? Maybe they won't be חולין בטהרה, chullin betaharah,
they'll touch somebody else's חולין. chullin. That's one thing, what about happens
when the risk is much greater like in this scenario that I
drew? I think that it's not so פשוט pashut that you just
turn a blind eye and or take a position of naivete and
assume תשובה teshuvah always always works. It's but yes, we should encourage
תשובה teshuvah and be prepared and so on and have open arms,
but there's also the question about the community.
I agree that you would buy something from them, you would...
Yes, so there is a risk here. There is a risk. I'm
not saying there's no risk.
But it's less severe.
Right, that's my point.
You'd buy something from them that you thought that טבל tevel was
already taken.
This is more about טהרות taharos and חולין בטהרה, chullin betaharah, but
there is some risk. Okay, but the point again is that that's
my point, right? Would you necessarily say we have to, the same
principle applies even if the risk is more severe? That's the question
that I am leaving us with. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this, תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan. בראשונה היו אומרים, berishonah hayu
omrim, חבר שנעשה גבאי chaver shena'asah gabbai דוחקין אותו מחברותו. dochakin oso
mechavruso. So here you again have the tax collectors. It's so fascinating,
this dichotomy or whatever, this sense of the opposite of the חבר
Chaver. is the tax collector. So somebody who was a tax collector
who has then made, now גבאי gabbai is not
even exactly a tax collector. A מוכס mochs is a tax collector.
A גבאי gabbai could be somebody that even is somebody that collects
internal, גבאי gabbai is somebody like, a מוכס mochs is a tax
collector for the Roman government. Okay, a גבאי gabbai could be somebody
that collects taxes internally for the Jewish community to use it to
distribute to the עניים aniyim or so on. But nevertheless, somehow that
is seen as being like
oppositional. I really don't fully get why. Maybe because maybe because they
have to go into everybody's homes for that means... What's the term?
מוכס. Mochs.
Now רש"י Rashi actually says גבאי gabbai is the same because normally
גבאות gabba'us in the sense of collecting צדקה tzedakah money is a
very
חשוב chashuv status. So if you look at רש"י Rashi by גבאי,
gabbai, רש"י Rashi says ממונה למלך לגבות מס מישראל. memuneh lamelech ligbos
mas miYisrael. So רש"י basically says the גבאי gabbai is the מוכס.
mochs. Okay, is the tax collector for the foreign government. And that
certainly we understand the contrast. So let's take a look. Although even
though we understand he's a bad guy, why he's the opposite of
a חבר chaver is not exactly clear. Anyway, somebody was a חבר
chaver, and then they got this post. דוחקין אותו מחברותו. Dochakin oso
mechavruso.
He then gets kicked out of the community. פירש אין מקבלין אותו.
Perash ein mekabelin oso.
And if he leaves his role of tax collector, we don't just
re-accept him. Again, that's the question, right? Like the אשת עם הארץ
eshes am ha'aretz who then does she was married to a חבר,
married to a עם הארץ am ha'aretz and then he dies, does
she immediately adopt back to her own status? Or this is like
the guy that's backslid and now wants to be re-accepted, the תשובה
teshuvah scenario. Do we automatically re-accept? And the answer is no. חזרו
לומר. Chazru lomar.
That's what they originally said, which sort of reflects the earlier approach
of we're not going to go with so open arms. חזרו לומר,
Chazru lomar, they reverted and said, פירש הרי הוא ככל אדם. perash
harei hu kechol adam. No, if he leaves his tax collecting, we'll
treat him like a normal person, which means he doesn't automatically re-assume
his status, but he can do a new formal acceptance. Right? There
are three possibilities: we refuse to ever accept you, you're automatically re-accepted,
or you need a new formal acceptance. So הרי הוא ככל אדם
harei hu kechol adam means you need a new formal acceptance,
like the more welcoming approach that we mentioned earlier. רב הונא בר
חייה איצטריכא ליה שעתא. Rav Huna bar Chiya itztricha lei sha'ata. So
רב הונא
בר חייה
Rav Huna bar
Chiya needed was like in a position where איצטריכא ליה שעתא itztricha
lei sha'ata is an idiomatic expression that basically means that he was
in a position where people really sought after him. Okay, for his
as a תלמיד חכם. chacham הוו על גביה רבה ורב יוסף. Havu
al gabei Rabbah veRav Yosef. So רבה Rabbah and רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, who were really seen as the biggest תלמידי חכמים
of the age, they went to him in order to learn תורה
from him. So וארבע מאה
זוגי
דרבנן. ve'arba me'ah zugei derabbanan.
And they went with 400 pairs of other student rabbis. Obviously, that's
a bit of an exaggeration. שמע דאתו. Shama de'asu. So he heard
they were coming. Oh my god, I'm going to have this very
חשוב chashuv delegation. By the way, איצטריכא ליה שעתא itztricha lei sha'ata
also suggests the sort of temporary nature of this status. Like maybe
he had a particular specialized area that everybody needed to learn from.
So they were coming with this huge rabbinic delegation to learn from
him. Okay, so שמע דאתו קטרי להו ארבע מאה תכתי. shama de'asu
katri lehu arba me'ah tachtei. So he bound for them or he
wove for them, whatever, 400 chairs. Okay, so he got out his
hemp or whatever, it's funny that it almost makes him like physically
making the chairs, prepared all the chairs, he's going to be teaching
all these חשוב chashuv rabbis. What? They said 400 pairs of זוגי
דרבנן. zugei derabbanan. . *Final check on "Talmid Chacham":* תלמיד חכם. *Final
check on "Bechor":* בכור. Bechor. *Final check on "Bechoros":* בכורות. Bechoros. *Final
check on "Korbanos":* קרבנות. Korbanos. *Final check on "Ma'aser Beheima":* מעשר בהמה.
Ma'aser Beheima. *Final check on "Tumah Vetaharah":* טומאה וטהרה. Tumah Vetaharah. *Final
check on "Mi'un":* מיאון. Mi'un. *Final check on "Chalitzah":* חליצה. Chalitzah. *Final
check on "Chashivus":* חשיבות. Chashivus. *Final check on "Gabbai":* גבאי. Gabbai. *Final
check on "Mumcheh":* מומחה. Mumcheh. *Final check on "Tanu Rabbanan":* תנו רבנן.
*Final check on "Amar Mar":* אמר מר. Amar Mar. *Final check on
"Bemai Askinan":* במאי עסקינן. Bemai askinan. *Final check on "Ilima Bechad":* אילימא
בחד. Ilima bechad. *Final check on "Mi Meheiman":* מי מהימן. Mi meheiman.
*Final check on "Ela Bislasa":* אלא בתלתא. Ela bislasa. *Final check on
"Umi Chashidi":* ומי חשידי. Umi chashidi. *Final check on "Vehatnan Vesanina":* והתנן
ותנינא. Vehatnan vesanina. *Final check on "Mipnei Shehu Beis Din":* מפני שהוא
בית דין. Mipnei shehu beis din. *Final check on "Le'olam Bechad":* לעולם
בחד. Le'olam bechad. *Final check on "Uchede'amar":* וכדאמר. Uchede'amar. *Final check on
"Beyachid":* ביחיד.
Beyachid. *Final check on "Ulesof shama denasiv gabbai":*
ולסוף שמע דניסב
גבאי.
Ulesof
shama denasiv gabbai.
*Final check on "Shalchu lei":* שלחו ליה. Shalchu lei. *Final check on
"Zil lachashivuseich zil
lekadmuseich":* זיל לחשיבותיך זיל לקדמותיך. Zil lachashivuseich zil lekadmuseich. *Final check on
"Shalach lehu":* שלח להו. Shalach lehu. *Final check on "Hadri bi":* הדרי
בי. Hadri bi. *Final check on "Rav Yosef lo azal":* רב יוסף
לא אזל. Rav Yosef lo azal. *Final check on "Rabba azal":* רבה
אזל. Rabba azal. *Final check on "Rav Yosef amar tanina":* רב יוסף
אמר תנינא. Rav Yosef amar tanina. *Final check on "Peireish ein mekabelin
oso":* פירש אין מקבלין אותו. Peireish ein mekabelin oso. *Final check on
"Rabba amar tanina":* רבה אמר תנינא. Rabba amar tanina. *Final check on
"Chasar lo harei hu kechol adam":* חזר לו הרי הוא ככל אדם.
Chasar lo harei hu kechol adam. *Final check on "Kol habechoros adam
ro'eh chutz mishel atzmo":* כל הבכורות אדם רואה חוץ משל עצמו. Kol
habechoros adam ro'eh chutz mishel atzmo. *Final check on "Vero'eh es kodashav":*
ורואה את קדשיו. Vero'eh es kodashav. *Final check on "Ve'es ma'asrosav":* ואת
מעשרותיו. Ve'es ma'asrosav. *Final check on "Venish'al al taharaso":* ונשאל על טהרתו.
Venish'al al taharaso. *Final check on "Mi shehayah o shehachlitzah befanav yis'enah":*
מי שהיה או שהחליצה בפניו ישאנה. Mi shehayah o shehachlitzah befanav yis'enah.
*Final check on "Uchede'amar Rav Chisda amar Rav Yochanan beyachid mumcheh":* וכדאמר
רב חסדא אמר רב יוחנן ביחיד מומחה. Uchede'amar Rav Chisda amar Rav
Yochanan beyachid mumcheh. *Final check on "Rabban and Yosef":* רבן Rabban and
יוסף. Yosef. *Final check on "Esav and Yaakov":* עשו Esav and יעקב.
Yaakov. *Final check on "Rav Yosef" and "Rabba":* רב יוסף Rav Yosef
and רבה. Rabba. *Final check on "Rav Chisda" and "Rav Yochanan":* רב
חסדא Rav Chisda and רב יוחנן. Rav Yochanan. *Final check on "Gemara"
and "Mishnah":* גמרא Gemara and משנה. Mishnah *Final check on "Beis Din":*
בית דין. Beis Din. *Final check on "Beis Hamikdash":* בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. *Final check on "Kohen":* כהן. Kohen. *Final check on "Heter":* היתר.
Heter. *Final check on "Psul":* פסול. Psul. *Final check on "Mum":* מום.
Mum. *Final check on "Chaver":* חבר. *Final check on "Talmid Chacham":* תלמיד
חכם. *Final check on "Bechor":* בכור. Bechor. *Final check on "Bechoros":* בכורות.
Bechoros. *Final check on "Korbanos":* קרבנות. Korbanos. *Final check on "Ma'aser Beheima":*
מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser Beheima. *Final check on "Tumah Vetaharah":* טומאה וטהרה. tumah
vetaharah? *Final check on "Mi'un":* מיאון. Mi'un. *Final check on "Chalitzah":* חליצה.
Chalitzah. *Final check on "Chashivus":* חשיבות. Chashivus. *Final check on "Gabbai":* גבאי.
Gabbai. *Final check on "Mumcheh":* מומחה. Mumcheh. *Final check on "Tanu Rabbanan":*
תנו רבנן. *Final check on "Amar Mar":* אמר מר. Amar Mar. *Final
check on "Bemai Askinan":* במאי עסקינן. Bemai askinan. *Final check on "Ilima
Bechad":* אילימא בחד. Ilima bechad. *Final check on "Mi Meheiman":* מי מהימן.
Mi meheiman. *Final check on "Ela Bislasa":* אלא בתלתא. Ela bislasa. *Final
check on "Umi Chashidi":* ומי חשידי. Umi chashidi. *Final check on "Vehatnan
Vesanina":* והתנן ותנינא. Vehatnan vesanina. *Final check on "Mipnei Shehu Beis Din":*
מפני שהוא בית דין. Mipnei shehu beis din. *Final check on "Le'olam
Bechad":* לעולם בחד. Le'olam bechad. *Final check on "Uchede'amar":* וכדאמר. Uchede'amar. *Final
check on "Beyachid":* ביחיד. Beyachid. *Final check on "Ulesof shama denasiv gabbai":*
ולסוף שמע דניסב גבאי. Ulesof shama denasiv gabbai. *Final check on "Shalchu
lei":* שלחו ליה. Shalchu lei. *Final check on "Zil lachashivuseich zil lekadmuseich":*
זיל לחשיבותיך זיל לקדמותיך. Zil lachashivuseich zil lekadmuseich. *Final check on "Shalach
lehu":* שלח להו. Shalach lehu. *Final check on "Hadri bi":* הדרי בי.
Hadri bi. *Final check on "Rav Yosef lo azal":* רב יוסף לא
אזל. Rav Yosef lo azal. *Final check on "Rabba azal":* רבה אזל.
Rabba azal. *Final check on "Rav Yosef amar tanina":* רב יוסף אמר
תנינא. Rav Yosef amar tanina. *Final check on "Peireish ein mekabelin oso":*
פירש אין מקבלין אותו if he's an expert, הכא נמי ביחיד מומחה.
hacha nami beyachid mumche. Here too, it could be one if he's
an expert, you don't need three. Now, that is very strange because
the whole idea and we'll talk about it later, we won't talk
about it now, but the whole idea why do you need three
for בכור? bechor? It's not a דין din of a בית דין.
Beis Din So why do you need three? But the direct analogy
to cases of normal דין and the same way sometimes one person
who is an expert can substitute for three, you know, again, that's
something taken out of סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, taken out of normal ways in
which a court operates, why you need three and why then the
exact analogy to בית דין is very unclear. But we will talk
about that later. For now, we can say that there is a
scenario where it could be just one and therefore we're afraid about
your partiality. I should also say when I was way back when,
when I was doing like, you know, intro psych in college, I
remember reading, you know, that they always assumed that that people like,
you know, that if you do things by committee, that it helps
negate any potential for like vested interest. You know, so like when
like contracts are awarded by committee and not just by one person
and in the individual, and that they actually found, again, I don't
know if I'm sure there's been other studies, but they've actually found
that it's not true. That actually, you know, if you're the one
person, then actually people know you're the responsible one and maybe דוקא
davka there you're more, you know, afraid to do something which will
be interpreted as, you know, as demonstrating partiality. Whereas if you're in
committee, there are subtle ways in which you can direct, you know,
the decision of the committee and there actually your own vested interest
is even less obvious. So it's an interesting question about like, you
know, how much is the concern about vested interest truly, you know,
truly negated when you are deal, you know, when you when you
sort of bring it into a group. Okay. Anyway, now the גמרא
Gemara goes on. ורואה את קדשיו, Veroeh es kodashav, so you why
can you inspect your own קדשים? kodashim? אי בעי מיתשיל עליה, Ee
baei misheil alei, because we're not so concerned about your partiality because
you could always, you know, do a התרה hatara for a for
when you sanctify something, it's like a verbal type of a נדר
neder or הפלאה, hafla'ah, and if you go to a חכם and
you do a התרה hatara you can undo it. So therefore, we're
not so concerned about partiality because there's other ways of getting out
of it. בכור Bechor there's no way of getting out of it.
ומעשרות, how about מעשר? maaser? You can't undo מעשר. maaser. So why
don't we concerned about partiality? דאי בעי שדי ביה מומא בכוליה עדרא.
De'ee baei shadi bei muma bechulei edra. Okay, because you could have
gotten out of it beforehand. Although right now maybe you can't, but
if you really were prepared to do something dishonest, that before you
took מעשר, maaser, you would have gone through your entire flock, made
a מום mum in every single sheep, so that whichever sheep was
the and then you would count, and the tenth, and whichever sheep
was the tenth, would already have a מום mum in it, and
you didn't do anything wrong because you made the מום mum before
it became מעשר. maaser. So if you really now of course that's
a funny point because that's if you were consciously dishonest and that
you would go to that extent. But here we're maybe afraid about
more subconscious partiality, but the גמרא Gemara says that's enough to say
that we're not concerned. ונישאל אטהרתיה, Venisheil ataharasei, why can you ask
answer a פסק psak question about your own טומאה tumah, וטהרה? דחזי
ליה בימי טומאתו, Dechazi lei bimei tumaso, because even if it was
טמא, tamei, you could eat it when you were טמא. tamei. Even
if you're normally careful about eating חולין בטהרה, you can eat it
בטומאה betumah when you happen to be טמא. tamei. תוספות Tosafos of
course says that's all very nice, but if it's תרומה terumah you
can't eat it when you're טמא. tamei. So why can you answer
a שאלה shaila about תרומה? terumah? Now more significant is this general
question. Can a rabbi פסקן pasken for himself for things that he
has a vested interest in? What is the rule, what is the
exception? It sounds like from this גמרא Gemara that the rule is
that you can't. The בכור, bechor, unless there's a particular reason why
in this case you know, you know, it doesn't make such of
such a big difference anyway. So if there was a way you
could have got the same result, then you can, but basically we
would be concerned about a vested interest. If you take a look
at the תוספות, Tosafos, תוספות Tosafos says, ודחזי ליה בימי טומאתו, vedechazi
lei bimei tumaso, תוספות Tosafos says, תימה ותרומה טמאה דלא חזי ליה.
teima uterumah temeiah d'lo chazi lei. How about let's say it's תרומה
טמאה? terumah temeiah? Let's say it's something that you really have a
vested interest in, that there's no other way to eat it without
your פסק. psak. וכי לא יהא נאמן? vechi lo yehei ne'eman? Do
we think you can't פסקן pasken for yourself? וכן בשאר כל איסור
והיתר? vechein bishar kol issur veheter? You know, all cases of פסקנינג.
paskening. Since when can you not פסקן pasken for yourself? ובהדיא אמרינן
בריש הדר, uvehedya amrinan bereish hadar, האי צורבא דרבנן חזי ליה לנפשיה.
hai tzurba derabanan chazi lei lenafshei. So there's גמרא Gemara that explicitly
talks about you inspecting something for yourself. Okay, that's one case. Now,
so this really is an interesting מחלוקת הפוסקים machlokes haposkim whether somebody
can פסקן pasken for themselves. And maybe there's a maybe they limit
it in all these cases we actually started with the fact except
maybe the טהרה's taharah case, with the fact that the thing was
assumed to be אסור assur and you have to now change its
status. It's not just an open question about the status, right? It
starts off being a בכור, bechor, מעשר, maaser, and you have to
change the status. So it gets even sharper if you have a
vested interest and it has a חזקת איסור, chezkas issur, right, and
you have to change that status, maybe you shouldn't be allowed to
פסקן pasken for yourselves. Not surprisingly, we we conclude that a פוסק
posek can פסקן pasken for himself even in these cases, but the
question is if you are the פוסק posek פסקנינג paskening that you
can פסקן pasken for yourself. From the circular problems, right? Because then
you aren't allowed to פסקן pasken that you could פסקן pasken for
yourself. Anyway, but that is, but certainly we do know, you know,
that רבנים rabbanim do, you know, פסקן pasken for themselves all along
and it's therefore, you know, as תוספות Tosafos says that certainly seems
clear from the גמרות, Gemaras, so it's not surprising that that's, you
know, that's sort of the conclusion that was reached, but it does
raise, you know, this גמרא Gemara doesn't sound that way. This גמרא
says the rule is actually, sounds like the rule is actually you
can't. Okay, so with that, yes, how does this apply to, to
rabbis who פסקן, pasken, right? I mean every person makes their own
judgments, halachic and otherwise, in their everyday lives. Right, and yeah, there's
something unique about טהרות or קדשים. kodshim. Right, so you have, right,
so that's a good way also of framing it, that since it's
in the larger context of חבר here, and although this is from
a משנה Mishnah in נדרים, Nedarim, in which, or no, the משנה
Mishnah is I think, yeah, נדרים Nedarim I think, anyway, but anyway,
but where's the original משנה Mishnah from? Yeah, נגעים, Negaim, I'm sorry,
נגעים. Negaim. So, but yes, but since the גמרא's context here is
חבר, then maybe what you're saying is like in the world of
טומאה, tumah, טהרה, taharah, קרבנות, korbanos, like those types of issues and
concerns, you know, there we'll adopt a higher standard and we want
total impartiality, at least as an ideal, or no concern, let me
reframe it, no concern of partiality. You know, and maybe distinguish, right,
the field of טומאה, טהרה, taharah, and קרבנות korbanos from other things.
Yes, that's definitely a possibility. Okay, הדרן לך כמה ישראלי חייב. hadran
lach kama yisraeli chayav. That was some packed פרק perek for a
קדשים kodshim פרק perek about some very, very relevant issues elsewhere. Now
we move back to the world of קדשים. kodshim. Let's at least
get started with the next פרק. perek. כל פסולי המוקדשים, kol pesulei
hamukdashim, all invalid קרבנות, korbanos, meaning a קרבן korban got a מום,
mum, and now you're going to redeem it, and everybody I assume
remembers, right, after you redeem a קרבן korban with a מום, mum,
it still retains some level of קדושה, kedushah, you can't shear it,
you can't work it. But there's another difference. A קרבן korban with
a מום mum you redeem. What do you do with a בכור
bechor with a מום? mum? Burn? What? No, buried if you didn't
שחט shecht it, but you שחט shecht it and you eat it.
Okay, so there is that difference. So that translates the following way.
So normal קרבנות korbanos with a מום, mum, there's a question whether
this phrase is in the משנה or not, but we'll read it
because it's anyway, הנאה להקדש. hana'ah lehekdesh. If they're going to redeem
it, הקדש hekdesh is going to benefit, right? If the animal's worth
a hundred dollars, you're going to redeem it on a hundred dollars
and you'll buy a new קרבן korban for a hundred. If it's
worth a thousand, you'll redeem it on a thousand, buy a new
קרבן. korban. So in the end, the הקדש hekdesh benefit, it's still
going to get the value of this animal. And therefore here's how
it translates. נמכרין באטליז ונשחטין באטליז. nimkarin be'itliz u'nishchatin be'itliz. They can
be sold in the butcher marketplace and they can be שחט shechted
in the butcher marketplace. ונשקלין בליטרין, venishkalin belitrin, and they can be
weighed out with pounds. What does that mean? It means that there's
a certain בזיון bizayon of קדשים kodshim if you go ahead and
put them, you know, in the meat market, right? The whole place
is a בלגן balagan and it smells and the whole thing. Now,
you have redeemed them. It's true. But even after you've redeemed them,
right, they are, you know, is it a proper treatment of קדשים,
kodshim, of things that used to be קדשים, kodshim, פסולי מוקדשים, pesulei
mukdashim, to be selling them in the meat market, to be שחט
shechting them in the meat market and so on? And the answer
is yes, that's a concern, but we will ignore it because הקדש
hekdesh benefits. If we did not let you שחט shecht it and
sell it in the meat market and weigh out the, you know,
how much per pound, then its value is going to be a
lot less. If we basically told you you have to eat it
at home or sell it privately, you're going to get a lot
less money. And therefore that means that when you figure out how
much do I redeem it for, הקדש hekdesh is going to get
a lot less money. Oh, I can only get two hundred dollars
for this, so I only have to redeem it on two hundred
dollars. But if you're going to let me sell it in the
market and I can sell it retail, not wholesale, I get a
thousand dollars for it, so it's worth a thousand dollars. So now
הקדש hekdesh will get a thousand dollars when I redeem it. חוץ
מן הבכור והמעשר, chutz min habechor ve'hama'aser, with the exception of בכור
bechor and מעשר, ma'aser, since you're not going to sell it and
you're only going to, you're only allowed to eat it, right, and
you're not, I shouldn't say not, you're not going to redeem it,
right? הקדש hekdesh is not going to get its value. You're the
one that's going to eat it with the מום. mum. So let's
say you don't want to eat it. Let's say you want to
sell it. Okay, but then it would be a בזיון bizayon קדשים
kodshim and הקדש hekdesh doesn't benefit because you're never going to redeem
it and it's never going to translate into value for הקדש. hekdesh.
So in that case, why not sell it anyway? בכור bechor and
מעשר? ma'aser? Well, they are yours and they, well, we're going to
talk in the גמרא about מעשר. ma'aser. But basically, the point is
they have to be eaten. Okay, so why should you not be
allowed to sell? By a כהן? kohen? מעשר ma'aser first of all
is by the owner, the ישראל, Yisrael, and the בכור bechor also
not by a כהן, kohen, it's not brought as a קרבן, korban,
it's the ממון mamon of a כהן, kohen, and once it has
a מום mum anybody can eat it. Okay, so therefore in that
case, since you're not going to redeem it, it doesn't matter what
you value it at, הקדש hekdesh isn't going to benefit. So we're
going to put more restrictions on you in order to show the
respect for this פסולי מוקדשים. pesulei mukdashim. So there, שהנאה לבעלים, she'hana'ah
labe'alim, it's only the owners that benefit, שהנאה לבעלים, she'hana'ah labe'alim, fine.
פסולי מוקדשים, pesulei mukdashim, and therefore, and the implicit point is, and
therefore you cannot sell it in the market and weigh it out.
You can only do like a private wholesale sale. פסולי מוקדשים שנעשה
להקדש Psulei mukdashim shanaise lehekdesh and now we can just say that
phrase, which is why it was taken out earlier, but this is
in the גרסא girsa earlier. Anyway, so in normal פסולי מוקדשים psulei
mukdashim הקדש hekdesh benefits, שוקלין מנה כנגד מנה בבכור. shoklin mane keneged
mane be'bechor. The one thing we do let you do by בכור
bechor is not to weigh it out with like, you know, those
pound weights, but let's say James comes here and I'm not doing
it in the marketplace, I'm doing it from my home, and James
comes and he wants to buy some of my בכור bechor meat.
So I can't go ahead and take my weights and put them
on the scale, but James says, look, here's a pound of meat
I bought from the butcher, I'd like an equal amount from your
lamb, from your בכור. bechor. So then I can do a balance
and weigh out an equal amount of meat to what James has.
That's less seen as like business-like and commercial and so on, it's
just making sure I'm giving him a pound, right? Not a trade,
you're not giving it to me, but I'm weighing it against an
equal amount of meat. It's somehow less businessy and less commercial. I'm
not giving it to him, I'm selling it. I am selling it
to you. I'm allowed to sell it to you, but only from
the back of my house, not in the market, and not by
using like the little pound weights and so on, but I can
do it like an equal amount of weight that's to some similar
amount of meat. And we will have to pick up with all
of this tomorrow. So, that was a fascinating דף, we're a little
behind.